<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>coreycholt on </title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in coreycholt on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Generative aRt in R</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ln3-09sep2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ln3-09sep2024/</guid>
      <description>Meet ✨geom_valley✨ I started writing this script at the end of 2021, inspired by The Ringer series by Dmitri Cherniak and Thomas Lin Pedersen&amp;rsquo;s Constructive collection.&#xA;I was back home in sunny Wales and set about trying to use a series of random choices to produce a cartoon landscape. I make a lot of data visualisations in R and it occurred to me that I could use ggplot functions if I just consider components of the image in terms of points along two axes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An unconventional host</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ln2-12aug2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ln2-12aug2024/</guid>
      <description>Beyond a handful of model or commercial species, invertebrate microbiomes are vastly understudied. However, these animals, and these animal-microbe interactions in particular, are vital for ecosystem functioning.&#xA;Many people will be unfamiliar with the tiny invertebrates that support aquatic environments. Therefore, stressing the importance of these host-microbe interactions and their implications for wider environmental health can be challenging.&#xA;Artemia, or brine shrimp, are incredibly important for aquatic food production (thousands of tonnes are produced each year as feed for other animals) but are perhaps better known to some by another name: Sea-Monkeys.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Source and variation of the amazing live Sea-Monkey microbiome</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2024_plosone/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2024_plosone/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, del Campo J, Keeling PJ. An embryonic diapause in unfavourable conditions has allowed brine shrimp to thrive in hypersaline environments and, unexpectedly, mail-order sachets and small, novelty tanks. Marketed as Sea-Monkeys®, each kit involves a 3-step process to generate adult Artemia within a matter of weeks. Whether these kits also allow for the maintenance of a host-associated microbiome is unclear. Therefore, comparing five replicate tanks under the same culture conditions, we sequenced the 16S ribosomal small subunit (SSU) gene to analyse bacterial community compositions in adults, their surrounding tank water, and their feed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Useful resources for data analysis</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/usefulresourcesformicrobiomeanalysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/usefulresourcesformicrobiomeanalysis/</guid>
      <description>Microbiomes: DADA2 I like to analyse all of my microbiome data directly in R with the DADA2 package. This is an Amplicon Sequence Variant (ASV) approach (meaning reads aren&#39;t clustered according to a similarity threshold) and relies on run-specific error models to denoise data and limit overestimations of sequence diversity. The DADA2 tutorial is a great place to start if you&#39;re interested in this method. Alternatively, you can implement DADA2 in QIIME2.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I made a website</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/ln1-27june2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/ln1-27june2024/</guid>
      <description>Now seemed like a good time to make a website. I wanted something that could be easily updated and personalised (with floating protists and invertebrates).&#xA;I landed on Hugo, a popular framework for generating static sites, and messed around with the winston-theme as best as I could. Don&amp;rsquo;t laugh at my butchered html and css files.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of heterotrophs reveals new insights in dinoflagellate evolution</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/cooney_2024_mbe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/cooney_2024_mbe/</guid>
      <description>Cooney EC, Holt CC, Hehenberger E, Adams JA, Leander BS, Keeling PJ. Dinoflagellates are diverse and ecologically important protists characterized by many morphological and molecular traits that set them apart from other eukaryotes. These features include, but are not limited to, massive genomes organized using bacterially-derived histone-like proteins (HLPs) and dinoflagellate viral nucleoproteins (DVNP) rather than histones, and a complex history of photobiology with many independent losses of photosynthesis, numerous cases of serial secondary and tertiary plastid gains, and the presence of horizontally acquired bacterial rhodopsins and type II RuBisCo.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coral-infecting parasites in cold marine ecosystems</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</guid>
      <description>Trznadel M, Holt CC, Livingston SJ, Kwong WK, Keeling PK. Coral reefs are a biodiversity hotspot and the association between coral and intracellular dinoflagellates is a model for endosymbiosis. Recently, corals and related anthozoans have also been found to harbor another kind of endosymbiont, apicomplexans called corallicolids. Apicomplexans are a diverse lineage of obligate intracellular parasites that include human pathogens such as the malaria parasite, Plasmodium. Global environmental sequencing shows corallicolids are tightly associated with tropical and subtropical reef environments where they infect diverse corals across a range of depths in many reef systems, and correlate with host mortality during bleaching events.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple parallel origins of parasitic Marine Alveolates</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Hehenberger E, Tikhonenkov DV, Jacko-Reynolds VKL, Okamoto N, Cooney EC, Irwin NAT, Keeling PK. *Equal Contribution Microbial eukaryotes are important components of marine ecosystems, and the Marine Alveolates (MALVs) are consistently both abundant and diverse in global environmental sequencing surveys. MALVs are dinoflagellates that are thought to be parasites of other protists and animals, but the lack of data beyond ribosomal RNA gene sequences from all but a few described species means much of their biology and evolution remain unknown.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial compartmentalisation of bacteria in phoronid microbiomes</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2023_scireports/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2023_scireports/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Dhaliwal S, Na I, Mtawali M, Boscaro V, Keeling PK. The phylum Phoronida comprises filter-feeding invertebrates that live in a protective tube sometimes reinforced with particulate material from the surrounding environments. Animals with these characteristics make promising candidate hosts for symbiotic bacteria, given the constant interactions with various bacterial colonizers, yet phoronids are one of the very few animal phyla with no available microbiome data whatsoever. Here, by sequencing the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene, we compare bacterial microbiomes in whole phoronids, including both tube and living tissues, with those associated exclusively to the isolated tube and/or the naked animal inside.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photosystems in the eye-like organelles of heterotrophic warnowiid dinoflagellates</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/cooney_2023_currentbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/cooney_2023_currentbio/</guid>
      <description>Cooney EC, Holt CC, Jacko-Reynolds VK, Leander BS, Keeling PJ. Warnowiid dinoflagellates contain a highly complex camera-eye-like structure called the ocelloid that is composed of different organelles resembling parts of metazoan eyes, including a modified plastid that serves as the retinal body. 1 The overall structure of the ocelloid has been investigated by microscopy; because warnowiids are not in culture and are rare in nature, we know little about their function.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic marine invertebrates are reservoirs for cryptic and diverse protists and fungi</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Boscaro V, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Mathur V, Irwin NA, Buckholtz G, Leander BS, Keeling PJ. Background: Microbial symbioses in marine invertebrates are commonplace. However, characterizations of invertebrate microbiomes are vastly outnumbered by those of vertebrates. Protists and fungi run the gamut of symbiosis, yet eukaryotic microbiome sequencing is rarely undertaken, with much of the focus on bacteria. To explore the importance of microscopic marine invertebrates as potential symbiont reservoirs, we used a phylogenetic-focused approach to analyze the host-associated eukaryotic microbiomes of 220 animal specimens spanning nine different animal phyla.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defining and averting syndemic pathways in aquaculture: a major global food sector</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2023_fronsusfood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2023_fronsusfood/</guid>
      <description>Stentiford GD, Tyler CR, Ellis RP, Bean TP, MacKenzie S, Brugere C, Holt CC, Peeler EJ, Christison KW, Rushton J, Bass D. Aquaculture now provides half of all aquatic protein consumed globally—with most current and future production occurring in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Concerns over the availability and application of effective policies to deliver safe and sustainable future supply have the potential to hamper further development of the sector. Creating healthy systems must extend beyond the simple exclusion of disease agents to tackle the host, environmental, and human drivers of poor outcomes and build new policies that incorporate these broader drivers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microbiomes of microscopic marine invertebrates do not reveal signatures of phylosymbiosis</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/boscaroholt_2023_naturemicro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/boscaroholt_2023_naturemicro/</guid>
      <description>Boscaro V*, Holt CC*, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Irwin NA, Álvarez-Campos P, Grzelak K, Holovachov O, Kerbl A, Mathur V, Okamoto N, Piercey RS, Worsaae K, Leander BS, Keeling PJ. *Equal Contribution Animals and microorganisms often establish close ecological relationships. However, much of our knowledge about animal microbiomes comes from two deeply studied groups: vertebrates and arthropods. To understand interactions on a broader scale of diversity, we characterized the bacterial microbiomes of close to 1,000 microscopic marine invertebrates from 21 phyla, spanning most of the remaining tree of metazoans.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global adoption of aquaculture to supply seafood</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2022_erl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2022_erl/</guid>
      <description>Stentiford GD, Holt CC. No abstract! Weird, eh?&#xA;Read the paper here Stentiford GD, Holt CC. Global adoption of aquaculture to supply seafood. Environmental Research Letters. 2022 Mar 21;17(4):041003.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A seafood risk tool for assessing and mitigating chemical and pathogen hazards in the aquaculture supply chain</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2022_naturefood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/stentiford_2022_naturefood/</guid>
      <description>Stentiford GD, Peeler EJ, Tyler CR, Bickley LK, Holt CC, Bass D, Turner AD, Baker-Austin C, Ellis T, Lowther JA, Posen PE, Bateman KS, Verner-Jeffreys DW, van van Aerle R, Stone DM, Paley R, Trent A, Katsiadaki I, Higman WG, Maskrey BH, Devlin MJ, Lyons BP, Hartnell DM, Younger AD, Bersuder P, Warford L, Losada S, Clarke K, Hynes C, Dewar A, Greenhill B, Huk M, Franks J, Dal-Molin F, Hartnell RE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the role of the shrimp gut microbiome in health and disease</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_jip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_jip/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Bass D, Stentiford GD, van der Giezen M. The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gut health in European lobster-the gut microbiome as a health marker in offshore sea culture</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC. The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster. Therefore, better characterisation of potential pathogens is vital to prevent collapse of any future culture initiative.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial and temporal axes impact ecology of the gut microbiome in juvenile European lobster (Homarus gammarus)</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_isme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2019_isme/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Van der Giezen M, Daniels CL, Stentiford GD, Bass D. Microbial communities within the gut can markedly impact host health and fitness. To what extent environmental influences affect the differential distribution of these microbial populations may therefore significantly impact the successful farming of the host. Using a sea-based container culture (SBCC) system for the on-growing of European lobster (Homarus gammarus), we tracked the bacterial gut microbiota over a 1-year period.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first clawed lobster virus Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV n. sp.) expands the diversity of the Nudiviridae</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</guid>
      <description>Holt CC, Stone M, Bass D, Bateman KS, van Aerle R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Ross SH, Hooper C, Stentiford GD. Viral diseases of crustaceans are increasingly recognised as challenges to shellfish farms and fisheries. Here we describe the first naturally-occurring virus reported in any clawed lobster species. Hypertrophied nuclei with emarginated chromatin, characteristic histopathological lesions of DNA virus infection, were observed within the hepatopancreatic epithelial cells of juvenile European lobsters (Homarus gammarus).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tart Cherry Concentrate Does Not Alter the Gut Microbiome, Glycaemic Control or Systemic Inflammation in a Middle-Aged Population</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/bowtell_2019_nutrients/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/bowtell_2019_nutrients/</guid>
      <description>Lear R, O’Leary M, O’Brien Andersen L, Holt CC, Stensvold CR, van der Giezen M, Bowtell JL. Limited evidence suggests that the consumption of polyphenols may improve glycaemic control and insulin sensitivity. The gut microbiome produces phenolic metabolites and increases their bioavailability. A handful of studies have suggested that polyphenol consumption alters gut microbiome composition. There are no data available investigating such effects in polyphenol-rich Montmorency cherry (MC) supplementation. A total of 28 participants (aged 40–60 years) were randomized to receive daily MC or glucose and energy-matched placebo supplementation for 4 wk.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halioticida noduliformans infection in eggs of lobster (Homarus gammarus) reveals its generalist parasitic strategy in marine invertebrates</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2018_jip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/publications/holt_2018_jip/</guid>
      <description>Holt C, Foster R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Feist SW, Stentiford GD, Bass D. A parasite exhibiting Oomycete-like morphology and pathogenesis was isolated from discoloured eggs of the European lobster (Homarus gammarus) and later found in gill tissues of adults. Group-specific Oomycete primers were designed to amplify the 18S ribosomal small subunit (SSU), which initially identified the organism as the same as the ‘Haliphthoros’ sp. NJM 0034 strain (AB178865.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Us</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to The Holt Lab! We&amp;rsquo;re based at the University of Bath in the United Kingdom. Our research currently spans four key themes &amp;hellip;&#xA;Microbiomes. We&#39;re interested in all things microbial diversity, particularly how and why microbes live in particular hosts or environments. These communities of microbes (i.e., microbiomes) can be integral to host and/or ecosystem functioning and we want to better understand how microbes fit into the web of processes that govern various environments.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethics and Values</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/ethicsAndValues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/ethicsAndValues/</guid>
      <description>This is a living document which details the values and expectations of The Holt Lab. I anticipate this to change and grow with the lab. Anyone thinking about joining our team should ensure they are happy to support the principles outlined in this document. Many of the policies discussed here are based on those from the Meren lab and Hammond Lab.&#xA;The Holt Lab welcomes all identities, be those related to gender, race, ethnicity, socio-economic status, sexuality, disability, etc.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/people/</guid>
      <description>Well, this is awkward &amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s just me at the moment.&#xA;Corey C. Holt Lecturer/Assistant Professor Corey, originally from Wales, completed his undergraduate degree and PhD at the University of Exeter. He was mostly based at the Centre for Environment, Fisheries, and Aquaculture Science (CEFAS), where he characterised microbes impacting lobster production using a novel sea-based culture system. He later moved to Canada to explore more fundamental questions of host-microbe associations in invertebrates, with a particular focus of protist diversity.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
