<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Protists on </title>
    <link>/tags/protists/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Protists on </description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/protists/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Four opportunities to join the Holt lab</title>
      <link>/posts/ln5-21nov2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/ln5-21nov2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are several opportunities to join the Holt lab next year! We have four PhD studentships for October 2026 competing for various studentships.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/identifying-signatures-of-host-specificity-in-protist-parasite-genomes/?p187771&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;display:inline;&#34;&gt;Identifying signatures of host specificity in protist parasite genomes.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Funded by the University of Bath’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bath.ac.uk/campaigns/university-research-studentship-award-ursa/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;URSA&lt;/a&gt; scheme and in collaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vickyhuntlab.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Vicky Hunt&lt;/a&gt; (University of Bath).&#xA;Deadline: December 3rd, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/swbio-dtp-phd-project-decoding-protist-parasites-in-aquaculture-with-single-cell-sequencing/?p190126&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;display:inline;&#34;&gt;Decoding Protist Parasites in Aquaculture with Single-Cell Sequencing.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.swbio.ac.uk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SWBio DTP&lt;/a&gt; and in collaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.swansea.ac.uk/staff/c.e.davies/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Charlotte Davies&lt;/a&gt; (Swansea University) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://researchportal.bath.ac.uk/en/persons/edward-feil/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Ed Feil&lt;/a&gt; (University of Bath).&#xA;Deadline: December 3rd, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Come join the Holt lab</title>
      <link>/posts/ln4-09oct2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/ln4-09oct2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in protist parasites and keen to learn some fun bioinformatics, take a look at our PhD project &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.findaphd.com/phds/project/identifying-signatures-of-host-specificity-in-protist-parasites-genomes/?p187771&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;currently being advertised!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The project &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Identifying signatures of host specificity in protist parasites genomes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; aims to leverage existing genomic data to model predictors of host range. Initially computer-based, the student will then test their predictions in the lab and in the field, looking for protists of interest in newly predicted hosts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenomic resolution of marine to freshwater dinoflagellate transitions</title>
      <link>/publications/mtawali_2025_isme/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/mtawali_2025_isme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;mtawali-m-cooney-ec-adams-j-jin-j-holt-cc-keeling-pk&#34;&gt;Mtawali M, Cooney EC, Adams J, Jin J, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Keeling PK.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dinoflagellates are an abundant and diverse group of protists that inhabit aquatic environments worldwide. They are characterized by numerous unique cellular and molecular traits, and have adapted to an unusually broad range of life strategies, including phototrophy, heterotrophy, parasitism, and all combinations of these. For most microbial groups, transitions from marine to freshwater environments are relatively rare, as changes in salinity are thought to lead to significant osmotic challenges that are difficult for the cell to overcome. Recent work has shown that dinoflagellates have overcome these challenges relatively often in evolutionary time, but because this is mostly based on single gene trees with low overall support, many of the relationships between freshwater and marine groups remain unresolved. Normally, phylogenomics could clarify such conclusions, but despite the recent surge in data, virtually no freshwater dinoflagellates have been characterized at the genome-wide level. Here, we generated 30 transcriptomes from cultures and single cells collected from freshwater environments to infer a robustly supported phylogenomic tree from 217 conserved genes, resolving at least seven transitions to freshwater in dinoflagellates. Mapping the distribution of ASVs from freshwater environmental samples onto this tree confirms these groups and identifies additional lineages where freshwater dinoflagellates likely remain unsampled. We also sampled two species of &lt;i&gt;Durinskia&lt;/i&gt;, a genus of “dinotoms” with both marine and freshwater lineages containing &lt;i&gt;Nitzschia&lt;/i&gt;-derived tertiary plastids. Ribosomal RNA phylogenies show that the host cells are closely related, but their endosymbionts are likely descended from two distantly-related freshwater &lt;i&gt;Nitzschia&lt;/i&gt; species that were acquired in parallel and relatively recently.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of heterotrophs reveals new insights in dinoflagellate evolution</title>
      <link>/publications/cooney_2024_mbe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/cooney_2024_mbe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;cooney-ec-holt-cc-hehenberger-e-adams-ja-leander-bs-keeling-pj&#34;&gt;Cooney EC, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Hehenberger E, Adams JA, Leander BS, Keeling PJ.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dinoflagellates are diverse and ecologically important protists characterized by many morphological and molecular traits that set them apart from other eukaryotes. These features include, but are not limited to, massive genomes organized using bacterially-derived histone-like proteins (HLPs) and dinoflagellate viral nucleoproteins (DVNP) rather than histones, and a complex history of photobiology with many independent losses of photosynthesis, numerous cases of serial secondary and tertiary plastid gains, and the presence of horizontally acquired bacterial rhodopsins and type II RuBisCo. Elucidating how this all evolved depends on knowing the phylogenetic relationships between dinoflagellate lineages. Half of these species are heterotrophic, but existing molecular data is strongly biased toward the photosynthetic dinoflagellates due to their amenability to cultivation and prevalence in culture collections. These biases make it impossible to interpret the evolution of photosynthesis, but may also affect phylogenetic inferences that impact our understanding of character evolution. Here, we address this problem by isolating individual cells from the Salish Sea and using single cell, culture-free transcriptomics to expand molecular data for dinoflagellates to include 27 more heterotrophic taxa, resulting in a roughly balanced representation. Using these data, we performed a comprehensive search for proteins involved in chromatin packaging, plastid function, and photoactivity across all dinoflagellates. These searches reveal that 1) photosynthesis was lost at least 21 times, 2) two known types of HLP were horizontally acquired around the same time rather than sequentially as previously thought; 3) multiple rhodopsins are present across the dinoflagellates, acquired multiple times from different donors; 4) kleptoplastic species have nucleus-encoded genes for proteins targeted to their temporary plastids and they are derived from multiple lineages, and 5) warnowiids are the only heterotrophs that retain a whole photosystem, although some photosynthesis-related electron transport genes are widely retained in heterotrophs, likely as part of the iron-sulfur cluster pathway that persists in non-photosynthetic plastids.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coral-infecting parasites in cold marine ecosystems</title>
      <link>/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;trznadel-m-holt-cc-livingston-sj-kwong-wk-keeling-pk&#34;&gt;Trznadel M, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Livingston SJ, Kwong WK, Keeling PK.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs are a biodiversity hotspot and the association between coral and intracellular dinoflagellates is a model for endosymbiosis. Recently, corals and related anthozoans have also been found to harbor another kind of endosymbiont, apicomplexans called corallicolids. Apicomplexans are a diverse lineage of obligate intracellular parasites that include human pathogens such as the malaria parasite, Plasmodium. Global environmental sequencing shows corallicolids are tightly associated with tropical and subtropical reef environments where they infect diverse corals across a range of depths in many reef systems, and correlate with host mortality during bleaching events. All of this points to corallicolids being ecologically significant to coral reefs, but it is also possible they are even more widely distributed because most environmental sampling is biased against parasites that maintain a tight association with their hosts throughout their life cycle. We tested the global distribution of corallicolids using a more direct approach, by specifically targeting potential anthozoan host animals from cold/temperate marine waters outside the coral reef context. We found that corallicolids are in fact common in such hosts, in some cases at high frequency, and that they infect the same tissue as parasites from topical coral reefs. Parasite phylogeny suggests corallicolids move between hosts and habitats relatively frequently, but that biogeography is more conserved. Overall, these results greatly expand the range of corallicolids beyond coral reefs, suggesting they are globally distributed parasites of marine anthozoans, which also illustrates significant blind spots that result from strategies commonly used to sample microbial biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple parallel origins of parasitic Marine Alveolates</title>
      <link>/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-hehenberger-e-tikhonenkov-dv-jacko-reynolds-vkl-okamoto-n-cooney-ec-irwin-nat-keeling-pk-equal-contribution&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Hehenberger E&lt;/em&gt;, Tikhonenkov DV, Jacko-Reynolds VKL, Okamoto N, Cooney EC, Irwin NAT, Keeling PK. *Equal Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Microbial eukaryotes are important components of marine ecosystems, and the Marine Alveolates (MALVs) are consistently both abundant and diverse in global environmental sequencing surveys. MALVs are dinoflagellates that are thought to be parasites of other protists and animals, but the lack of data beyond ribosomal RNA gene sequences from all but a few described species means much of their biology and evolution remain unknown. Using single-cell transcriptomes from several MALVs and their free-living relatives, we show that MALVs evolved independently from two distinct, free-living ancestors and that their parasitism evolved in parallel. Phylogenomics shows one subgroup (MALV-II and -IV, or Syndiniales) is related to a novel lineage of free-living, eukaryovorous predators, the eleftherids, while the other (MALV-I, or Ichthyodinida) is related to the free-living predator Oxyrrhis and retains proteins targeted to a non-photosynthetic plastid. Reconstructing the evolution of photosynthesis, plastids, and parasitism in early-diverging dinoflagellates shows a number of parallels with the evolution of their apicomplexan sisters. In both groups, similar forms of parasitism evolved multiple times and photosynthesis was lost many times. By contrast, complete loss of the plastid organelle is infrequent and, when this does happen, leaves no residual genes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic marine invertebrates are reservoirs for cryptic and diverse protists and fungi</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-boscaro-v-van-steenkiste-nw-herranz-m-mathur-v-irwin-na-buckholtz-g-leander-bs-keeling-pj&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Boscaro V, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Mathur V, Irwin NA, Buckholtz G, Leander BS, Keeling PJ.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Background: Microbial symbioses in marine invertebrates are commonplace. However, characterizations of invertebrate microbiomes are vastly outnumbered by those of vertebrates. Protists and fungi run the gamut of symbiosis, yet eukaryotic microbiome sequencing is rarely undertaken, with much of the focus on bacteria. To explore the importance of microscopic marine invertebrates as potential symbiont reservoirs, we used a phylogenetic-focused approach to analyze the host-associated eukaryotic microbiomes of 220 animal specimens spanning nine different animal phyla.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Results: Our data expanded the traditional host range of several microbial taxa and identified numerous undescribed lineages. A lack of comparable reference sequences resulted in several cryptic clades within the Apicomplexa and Ciliophora and emphasized the potential for microbial invertebrates to harbor novel protistan and fungal diversity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Conclusions: Microscopic marine invertebrates, spanning a wide range of animal phyla, host various protist and fungal sequences and may therefore serve as a useful resource in the detection and characterization of undescribed symbioses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gut health in European lobster-the gut microbiome as a health marker in offshore sea culture</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster. Therefore, better characterisation of potential pathogens is vital to prevent collapse of any future culture initiative. The community of microorganisms within the gut, referred to as the gut microbiome, is involved in key metabolic processes affecting host health and fitness and may serve as a key resource in reducing susceptibility to pathogenesis. Here we utilise a series of histological and molecular techniques to better characterise lobster disease and the lobster gut microbiome and assess the use of sea-based container culture (SBCC) as a means to culture the species and overcome the bottlenecks associated with traditional land-based culture (LBC). In assessing mortality of land-based larvae and egg clutches entering the hatchery, we first detected the abalone parasite Haliphthoros milfordensis. Histological and molecular characterisation of this parasitic oomycete confirm past suspicions that H. milfordensis and Halocrusticida noduliformans are one and the same, highlighting the lack of available information surrounding animal oomycete pathogens. To facilitate monitoring of the parasite and growth of the literature, we developed and tested general oomycete primers, targeting the 18S ribosomal small sub-unit (SSU) and revealed a wealth of oomycete diversity in freshwater, marine water and soil samples. Monitoring health of deployed juveniles in SBCC, we observed histological signs of viral infection. Genome characterisation and phylogenetic reconstruction revealed the virus to be a new member of the Nudivirdae. Thus, we discovered the first described clawed-lobster virus: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). The double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) virus, containing 107 063 bp contains the conserved repertoire of genes associated with the nudiviruses yet does not form occlusion bodies, characteristic of its neighbouring lineages. We compared viral prevalence in SBCC to LBC and questioned the transmission strategy of this novel virus in the absence of occlusion. Utilising high-throughput amplicon sequencing, we characterised the bacterial gut microbiome of the European lobster using the V4 region of the ribosomal SSU. We compared communities assembled in SBCC with those found LBC and assessed culture and time-dependent determinants of community structure and assembly. Typical of other aquatic invertebrates, the gut of juvenile European lobster mainly harboured Vibrio spp. but became more diverse as the host ages. Assessing phylogenetic structuring of the community, SBCC encouraged more deterministic assembly of the gut microbiome and reduced stochasticity observed in LBC. Furthermore, the gut microbiome of individuals reared in SBCC was significantly more diverse that those reared in LBC. A more diverse gut is thought to be beneficial to host health. In support of this theory, a reduction in bacterial gut diversity was associated with the detection of HgNV in the digestive tract, which was less prevalent in SBCC populations compared to the hatchery. Together, this information suggests that SBCC may support the culture of a healthy population through the assembly of a more beneficial gut community with the potential to provide resistance against infection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halioticida noduliformans infection in eggs of lobster (Homarus gammarus) reveals its generalist parasitic strategy in marine invertebrates</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2018_jip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2018_jip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-c-foster-r-daniels-cl-van-der-giezen-m-feist-sw-stentiford-gd-bass-d&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt C&lt;/u&gt;, Foster R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Feist SW, Stentiford GD, Bass D.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A parasite exhibiting Oomycete-like morphology and pathogenesis was isolated from discoloured eggs of the European lobster (Homarus gammarus) and later found in gill tissues of adults. Group-specific Oomycete primers were designed to amplify the 18S ribosomal small subunit (SSU), which initially identified the organism as the same as the ‘Haliphthoros’ sp. NJM 0034 strain (AB178865.1) previously isolated from abalone (imported from South Australia to Japan). However, in accordance with other published SSU-based phylogenies, the NJM 0034 isolate did not group with other known Haliphthoros species in our Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian phylogenies. Instead, the strain formed an orphan lineage, diverging before the separation of the Saprolegniales and Pythiales. Based upon 28S large subunit (LSU) phylogeny, our own isolate and the previously unidentified 0034 strain are both identical to the abalone pathogen Halioticida noduliformans. The genus shares morphological similarities with Haliphthoros and Halocrusticida and forms a clade with these in LSU phylogenies. Here, we confirm the first recorded occurrence of H. noduliformans in European lobsters and associate its presence with pathology of the egg mass, likely leading to reduced fecundity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
