<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MALVs on </title>
    <link>/tags/malvs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in MALVs on </description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/malvs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Multiple parallel origins of parasitic Marine Alveolates</title>
      <link>/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holthehenberger_2023_naturecomms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-hehenberger-e-tikhonenkov-dv-jacko-reynolds-vkl-okamoto-n-cooney-ec-irwin-nat-keeling-pk-equal-contribution&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;&lt;em&gt;, Hehenberger E&lt;/em&gt;, Tikhonenkov DV, Jacko-Reynolds VKL, Okamoto N, Cooney EC, Irwin NAT, Keeling PK. *Equal Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Microbial eukaryotes are important components of marine ecosystems, and the Marine Alveolates (MALVs) are consistently both abundant and diverse in global environmental sequencing surveys. MALVs are dinoflagellates that are thought to be parasites of other protists and animals, but the lack of data beyond ribosomal RNA gene sequences from all but a few described species means much of their biology and evolution remain unknown. Using single-cell transcriptomes from several MALVs and their free-living relatives, we show that MALVs evolved independently from two distinct, free-living ancestors and that their parasitism evolved in parallel. Phylogenomics shows one subgroup (MALV-II and -IV, or Syndiniales) is related to a novel lineage of free-living, eukaryovorous predators, the eleftherids, while the other (MALV-I, or Ichthyodinida) is related to the free-living predator Oxyrrhis and retains proteins targeted to a non-photosynthetic plastid. Reconstructing the evolution of photosynthesis, plastids, and parasitism in early-diverging dinoflagellates shows a number of parallels with the evolution of their apicomplexan sisters. In both groups, similar forms of parasitism evolved multiple times and photosynthesis was lost many times. By contrast, complete loss of the plastid organelle is infrequent and, when this does happen, leaves no residual genes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic marine invertebrates are reservoirs for cryptic and diverse protists and fungi</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-boscaro-v-van-steenkiste-nw-herranz-m-mathur-v-irwin-na-buckholtz-g-leander-bs-keeling-pj&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Boscaro V, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Mathur V, Irwin NA, Buckholtz G, Leander BS, Keeling PJ.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Background: Microbial symbioses in marine invertebrates are commonplace. However, characterizations of invertebrate microbiomes are vastly outnumbered by those of vertebrates. Protists and fungi run the gamut of symbiosis, yet eukaryotic microbiome sequencing is rarely undertaken, with much of the focus on bacteria. To explore the importance of microscopic marine invertebrates as potential symbiont reservoirs, we used a phylogenetic-focused approach to analyze the host-associated eukaryotic microbiomes of 220 animal specimens spanning nine different animal phyla.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Results: Our data expanded the traditional host range of several microbial taxa and identified numerous undescribed lineages. A lack of comparable reference sequences resulted in several cryptic clades within the Apicomplexa and Ciliophora and emphasized the potential for microbial invertebrates to harbor novel protistan and fungal diversity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Conclusions: Microscopic marine invertebrates, spanning a wide range of animal phyla, host various protist and fungal sequences and may therefore serve as a useful resource in the detection and characterization of undescribed symbioses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
