<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Virus on </title>
    <link>/tags/virus/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Virus on </description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/virus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gut health in European lobster-the gut microbiome as a health marker in offshore sea culture</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster. Therefore, better characterisation of potential pathogens is vital to prevent collapse of any future culture initiative. The community of microorganisms within the gut, referred to as the gut microbiome, is involved in key metabolic processes affecting host health and fitness and may serve as a key resource in reducing susceptibility to pathogenesis. Here we utilise a series of histological and molecular techniques to better characterise lobster disease and the lobster gut microbiome and assess the use of sea-based container culture (SBCC) as a means to culture the species and overcome the bottlenecks associated with traditional land-based culture (LBC). In assessing mortality of land-based larvae and egg clutches entering the hatchery, we first detected the abalone parasite Haliphthoros milfordensis. Histological and molecular characterisation of this parasitic oomycete confirm past suspicions that H. milfordensis and Halocrusticida noduliformans are one and the same, highlighting the lack of available information surrounding animal oomycete pathogens. To facilitate monitoring of the parasite and growth of the literature, we developed and tested general oomycete primers, targeting the 18S ribosomal small sub-unit (SSU) and revealed a wealth of oomycete diversity in freshwater, marine water and soil samples. Monitoring health of deployed juveniles in SBCC, we observed histological signs of viral infection. Genome characterisation and phylogenetic reconstruction revealed the virus to be a new member of the Nudivirdae. Thus, we discovered the first described clawed-lobster virus: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). The double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) virus, containing 107 063 bp contains the conserved repertoire of genes associated with the nudiviruses yet does not form occlusion bodies, characteristic of its neighbouring lineages. We compared viral prevalence in SBCC to LBC and questioned the transmission strategy of this novel virus in the absence of occlusion. Utilising high-throughput amplicon sequencing, we characterised the bacterial gut microbiome of the European lobster using the V4 region of the ribosomal SSU. We compared communities assembled in SBCC with those found LBC and assessed culture and time-dependent determinants of community structure and assembly. Typical of other aquatic invertebrates, the gut of juvenile European lobster mainly harboured Vibrio spp. but became more diverse as the host ages. Assessing phylogenetic structuring of the community, SBCC encouraged more deterministic assembly of the gut microbiome and reduced stochasticity observed in LBC. Furthermore, the gut microbiome of individuals reared in SBCC was significantly more diverse that those reared in LBC. A more diverse gut is thought to be beneficial to host health. In support of this theory, a reduction in bacterial gut diversity was associated with the detection of HgNV in the digestive tract, which was less prevalent in SBCC populations compared to the hatchery. Together, this information suggests that SBCC may support the culture of a healthy population through the assembly of a more beneficial gut community with the potential to provide resistance against infection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial and temporal axes impact ecology of the gut microbiome in juvenile European lobster (Homarus gammarus)</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_isme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_isme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-van-der-giezen-m-daniels-cl-stentiford-gd-bass-d&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Van der Giezen M, Daniels CL, Stentiford GD, Bass D.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Microbial communities within the gut can markedly impact host health and fitness. To what extent environmental influences affect the differential distribution of these microbial populations may therefore significantly impact the successful farming of the host. Using a sea-based container culture (SBCC) system for the on-growing of European lobster (Homarus gammarus), we tracked the bacterial gut microbiota over a 1-year period. We compared these communities with lobsters of the same cohort, retained in a land-based culture (LBC) system to assess the effects of the culture environment on gut bacterial assemblage and describe the phylogenetic structure of the microbiota to compare deterministic and stochastic assembly across both environments. Bacterial gut communities from SBCCs were generally more phylogenetically clustered, and therefore deterministically assembled, compared to those reared in land-based systems. Lobsters in SBCCs displayed significantly more species-rich and species-diverse gut microbiota compared to those retained in LBC. A reduction in the bacterial diversity of the gut was also associated with higher infection prevalence of the enteric viral pathogen Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). SBCCs may therefore benefit the overall health of the host by promoting the assembly of a more diverse gut bacterial community and reducing the susceptibility to disease.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first clawed lobster virus Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV n. sp.) expands the diversity of the Nudiviridae</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-stone-m-bass-d-bateman-ks-van-aerle-r-daniels-cl-van-der-giezen-m-ross-sh-hooper-c-stentiford-gd&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Stone M, Bass D, Bateman KS, van Aerle R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Ross SH, Hooper C, Stentiford GD.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Viral diseases of crustaceans are increasingly recognised as challenges to shellfish farms and fisheries. Here we describe the first naturally-occurring virus reported in any clawed lobster species. Hypertrophied nuclei with emarginated chromatin, characteristic histopathological lesions of DNA virus infection, were observed within the hepatopancreatic epithelial cells of juvenile European lobsters (Homarus gammarus). Transmission electron microscopy revealed infection with a bacilliform virus containing a rod shaped nucleocapsid enveloped in an elliptical membrane. Assembly of PCR-free shotgun metagenomic sequencing produced a circular genome of 107,063 bp containing 97 open reading frames, the majority of which share sequence similarity with a virus infecting the black tiger shrimp: Penaeus monodon nudivirus (PmNV). Multiple phylogenetic analyses confirm the new virus to be a novel member of the Nudiviridae: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). Evidence of occlusion body formation, characteristic of PmNV and its closest relatives, was not observed, questioning the horizontal transmission strategy of HgNV outside of the host. We discuss the potential impacts of HgNV on juvenile lobster growth and mortality and present HgNV-specific primers to serve as a diagnostic tool for monitoring the virus in wild and farmed lobster stocks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
