<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Invertebrates on </title>
    <link>/tags/invertebrates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Invertebrates on </description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/invertebrates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An unconventional host</title>
      <link>/posts/ln2-12aug2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/ln2-12aug2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Beyond a handful of model or commercial species, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5850079/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;invertebrate microbiomes are vastly understudied&lt;/a&gt;. However, these animals, and these animal-microbe interactions in particular, are vital for ecosystem functioning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many people will be unfamiliar with the tiny invertebrates that support aquatic environments. Therefore, stressing the importance of these host-microbe interactions and their implications for wider environmental health can be challenging.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artemia&lt;/em&gt;, or brine shrimp, are incredibly important for aquatic food production (thousands of tonnes are produced each year as feed for other animals) but are perhaps better known to some by another name: Sea-Monkeys.&#xA;Many of us have peered into Sea-Monkey tanks, willing our &amp;ldquo;instant pets&amp;rdquo; to finally hatch. Like a handful of other animals, brine shrimp can enter a period of suspended development, and this &amp;ldquo;diapause&amp;rdquo; is broken when the eggs are submerged in water. This means dehydrated eggs, which are remarkably stable, can be easily transported and reconstituted at a later date (be it in small, novelty tanks or otherwise).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Source and variation of the amazing live Sea-Monkey microbiome</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2024_plosone/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2024_plosone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-del-campo-j-keeling-pj&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, del Campo J, Keeling PJ.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An embryonic diapause in unfavourable conditions has allowed brine shrimp to thrive in hypersaline environments and, unexpectedly, mail-order sachets and small, novelty tanks. Marketed as Sea-Monkeys®, each kit involves a 3-step process to generate adult Artemia within a matter of weeks. Whether these kits also allow for the maintenance of a host-associated microbiome is unclear. Therefore, comparing five replicate tanks under the same culture conditions, we sequenced the 16S ribosomal small subunit (SSU) gene to analyse bacterial community compositions in adults, their surrounding tank water, and their feed. Adult Sea-Monkeys® harboured a bacterial microbiome that was clearly distinguishable from the tank water and food. Furthermore, individual tanks had a notable effect on fine-scale microbiome variation. Several Sea-Monkey bacterial variants appeared absent in environmental samples and included genera (&lt;i&gt;Leucobacter&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Microbacterium&lt;/i&gt;) known to confer desiccation resistance in other hosts. Although Sea-Monkeys® taxonomy is unclear, phylogenetic inference of the cytochrome c oxidase I (COXI) gene from the host animal suggests Sea-Monkeys® belong to the Artemia franciscana ‘superspecies’. Overall, Sea-Monkeys® kits appear to be a convenient and scalable mesocosm for the study of host-microbiome interactions and could serve as a useful tool for future invertebrate microbiome research, outreach, and education.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coral-infecting parasites in cold marine ecosystems</title>
      <link>/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/trznadel_2024_currentbio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;trznadel-m-holt-cc-livingston-sj-kwong-wk-keeling-pk&#34;&gt;Trznadel M, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Livingston SJ, Kwong WK, Keeling PK.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs are a biodiversity hotspot and the association between coral and intracellular dinoflagellates is a model for endosymbiosis. Recently, corals and related anthozoans have also been found to harbor another kind of endosymbiont, apicomplexans called corallicolids. Apicomplexans are a diverse lineage of obligate intracellular parasites that include human pathogens such as the malaria parasite, Plasmodium. Global environmental sequencing shows corallicolids are tightly associated with tropical and subtropical reef environments where they infect diverse corals across a range of depths in many reef systems, and correlate with host mortality during bleaching events. All of this points to corallicolids being ecologically significant to coral reefs, but it is also possible they are even more widely distributed because most environmental sampling is biased against parasites that maintain a tight association with their hosts throughout their life cycle. We tested the global distribution of corallicolids using a more direct approach, by specifically targeting potential anthozoan host animals from cold/temperate marine waters outside the coral reef context. We found that corallicolids are in fact common in such hosts, in some cases at high frequency, and that they infect the same tissue as parasites from topical coral reefs. Parasite phylogeny suggests corallicolids move between hosts and habitats relatively frequently, but that biogeography is more conserved. Overall, these results greatly expand the range of corallicolids beyond coral reefs, suggesting they are globally distributed parasites of marine anthozoans, which also illustrates significant blind spots that result from strategies commonly used to sample microbial biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial compartmentalisation of bacteria in phoronid microbiomes</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2023_scireports/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2023_scireports/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-dhaliwal-s-na-i-mtawali-m-boscaro-v-keeling-pk&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Dhaliwal S, Na I, Mtawali M, Boscaro V, Keeling PK.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The phylum Phoronida comprises filter-feeding invertebrates that live in a protective tube sometimes reinforced with particulate material from the surrounding environments. Animals with these characteristics make promising candidate hosts for symbiotic bacteria, given the constant interactions with various bacterial colonizers, yet phoronids are one of the very few animal phyla with no available microbiome data whatsoever. Here, by sequencing the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene, we compare bacterial microbiomes in whole phoronids, including both tube and living tissues, with those associated exclusively to the isolated tube and/or the naked animal inside. We also compare these communities with those from the surrounding water. Phoronid microbiomes from specimens belonging to the same colony but collected a month apart were significantly different, and bacterial taxa previously reported in association with invertebrates and sediment were found to drive this difference. The microbiomes associated with the tubes are very similar in composition to those isolated from whole animals. However, just over half of bacteria found in whole specimens are also found both in tubes and naked specimens. In conclusion, phoronids harbour bacterial microbiomes that differ from those in the surrounding water, but the composition of those microbiomes is not stable and appears to change in the same colony over a relatively short time frame. Considering individual spatial/anatomical compartments, the phoronid tube contributes most to the whole-animal microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic marine invertebrates are reservoirs for cryptic and diverse protists and fungi</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2023_microbiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-boscaro-v-van-steenkiste-nw-herranz-m-mathur-v-irwin-na-buckholtz-g-leander-bs-keeling-pj&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Boscaro V, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Mathur V, Irwin NA, Buckholtz G, Leander BS, Keeling PJ.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Background: Microbial symbioses in marine invertebrates are commonplace. However, characterizations of invertebrate microbiomes are vastly outnumbered by those of vertebrates. Protists and fungi run the gamut of symbiosis, yet eukaryotic microbiome sequencing is rarely undertaken, with much of the focus on bacteria. To explore the importance of microscopic marine invertebrates as potential symbiont reservoirs, we used a phylogenetic-focused approach to analyze the host-associated eukaryotic microbiomes of 220 animal specimens spanning nine different animal phyla.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Results: Our data expanded the traditional host range of several microbial taxa and identified numerous undescribed lineages. A lack of comparable reference sequences resulted in several cryptic clades within the Apicomplexa and Ciliophora and emphasized the potential for microbial invertebrates to harbor novel protistan and fungal diversity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Conclusions: Microscopic marine invertebrates, spanning a wide range of animal phyla, host various protist and fungal sequences and may therefore serve as a useful resource in the detection and characterization of undescribed symbioses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microbiomes of microscopic marine invertebrates do not reveal signatures of phylosymbiosis</title>
      <link>/publications/boscaroholt_2023_naturemicro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/boscaroholt_2023_naturemicro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;boscaro-v-holt-cc-van-steenkiste-nw-herranz-m-irwin-na-álvarez-campos-p-grzelak-k-holovachov-o-kerbl-a-mathur-v-okamoto-n-piercey-rs-worsaae-k-leander-bs-keeling-pj-equal-contribution&#34;&gt;Boscaro V*, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC*&lt;/u&gt;, Van Steenkiste NW, Herranz M, Irwin NA, Álvarez-Campos P, Grzelak K, Holovachov O, Kerbl A, Mathur V, Okamoto N, Piercey RS, Worsaae K, Leander BS, Keeling PJ. *Equal Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Animals and microorganisms often establish close ecological relationships. However, much of our knowledge about animal microbiomes comes from two deeply studied groups: vertebrates and arthropods. To understand interactions on a broader scale of diversity, we characterized the bacterial microbiomes of close to 1,000 microscopic marine invertebrates from 21 phyla, spanning most of the remaining tree of metazoans. Samples were collected from five temperate and tropical locations covering three marine habitats (sediment, water column and intertidal macroalgae) and bacterial microbiomes were characterized using 16S ribosomal RNA gene sequencing. Our data show that, despite their size, these animals harbour bacterial communities that differ from those in the surrounding environment. Distantly related but coexisting invertebrates tend to share many of the same bacteria, suggesting that guilds of microorganisms preferentially associated with animals, but not tied to any specific host lineage, are the main drivers of the ecological relationship. Host identity is a minor factor shaping these microbiomes, which do not show the same correlation with host phylogeny, or ‘phylosymbiosis’, observed in many large animals. Hence, the current debate on the varying strength of phylosymbiosis within selected lineages should be reframed to account for the possibility that such a pattern might be the exception rather than the rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the role of the shrimp gut microbiome in health and disease</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_jip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_jip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-bass-d-stentiford-gd-van-der-giezen-m&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Bass D, Stentiford GD, van der Giezen M.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster. Therefore, better characterisation of potential pathogens is vital to prevent collapse of any future culture initiative. The community of microorganisms within the gut, referred to as the gut microbiome, is involved in key metabolic processes affecting host health and fitness and may serve as a key resource in reducing susceptibility to pathogenesis. Here we utilise a series of histological and molecular techniques to better characterise lobster disease and the lobster gut microbiome and assess the use of sea-based container culture (SBCC) as a means to culture the species and overcome the bottlenecks associated with traditional land-based culture (LBC). In assessing mortality of land-based larvae and egg clutches entering the hatchery, we first detected the abalone parasite Haliphthoros milfordensis. Histological and molecular characterisation of this parasitic oomycete confirm past suspicions that H. milfordensis and Halocrusticida noduliformans are one and the same, highlighting the lack of available information surrounding animal oomycete pathogens. To facilitate monitoring of the parasite and growth of the literature, we developed and tested general oomycete primers, targeting the 18S ribosomal small sub-unit (SSU) and revealed a wealth of oomycete diversity in freshwater, marine water and soil samples. Monitoring health of deployed juveniles in SBCC, we observed histological signs of viral infection. Genome characterisation and phylogenetic reconstruction revealed the virus to be a new member of the Nudivirdae. Thus, we discovered the first described clawed-lobster virus: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). The double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) virus, containing 107 063 bp contains the conserved repertoire of genes associated with the nudiviruses yet does not form occlusion bodies, characteristic of its neighbouring lineages. We compared viral prevalence in SBCC to LBC and questioned the transmission strategy of this novel virus in the absence of occlusion. Utilising high-throughput amplicon sequencing, we characterised the bacterial gut microbiome of the European lobster using the V4 region of the ribosomal SSU. We compared communities assembled in SBCC with those found LBC and assessed culture and time-dependent determinants of community structure and assembly. Typical of other aquatic invertebrates, the gut of juvenile European lobster mainly harboured Vibrio spp. but became more diverse as the host ages. Assessing phylogenetic structuring of the community, SBCC encouraged more deterministic assembly of the gut microbiome and reduced stochasticity observed in LBC. Furthermore, the gut microbiome of individuals reared in SBCC was significantly more diverse that those reared in LBC. A more diverse gut is thought to be beneficial to host health. In support of this theory, a reduction in bacterial gut diversity was associated with the detection of HgNV in the digestive tract, which was less prevalent in SBCC populations compared to the hatchery. Together, this information suggests that SBCC may support the culture of a healthy population through the assembly of a more beneficial gut community with the potential to provide resistance against infection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gut health in European lobster-the gut microbiome as a health marker in offshore sea culture</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The European lobster (Homarus gammarus) represents one of the United Kingdom’s most valuable fisheries. High market prices and a relatively limited fishery suggests that the species may be a good candidate for aquaculture and/or further stock enhancement. Disease is one of the biggest threats to the development and progression of sustainable aquaculture. However very little is known in regard to diseases of the European lobster. Therefore, better characterisation of potential pathogens is vital to prevent collapse of any future culture initiative. The community of microorganisms within the gut, referred to as the gut microbiome, is involved in key metabolic processes affecting host health and fitness and may serve as a key resource in reducing susceptibility to pathogenesis. Here we utilise a series of histological and molecular techniques to better characterise lobster disease and the lobster gut microbiome and assess the use of sea-based container culture (SBCC) as a means to culture the species and overcome the bottlenecks associated with traditional land-based culture (LBC). In assessing mortality of land-based larvae and egg clutches entering the hatchery, we first detected the abalone parasite Haliphthoros milfordensis. Histological and molecular characterisation of this parasitic oomycete confirm past suspicions that H. milfordensis and Halocrusticida noduliformans are one and the same, highlighting the lack of available information surrounding animal oomycete pathogens. To facilitate monitoring of the parasite and growth of the literature, we developed and tested general oomycete primers, targeting the 18S ribosomal small sub-unit (SSU) and revealed a wealth of oomycete diversity in freshwater, marine water and soil samples. Monitoring health of deployed juveniles in SBCC, we observed histological signs of viral infection. Genome characterisation and phylogenetic reconstruction revealed the virus to be a new member of the Nudivirdae. Thus, we discovered the first described clawed-lobster virus: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). The double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) virus, containing 107 063 bp contains the conserved repertoire of genes associated with the nudiviruses yet does not form occlusion bodies, characteristic of its neighbouring lineages. We compared viral prevalence in SBCC to LBC and questioned the transmission strategy of this novel virus in the absence of occlusion. Utilising high-throughput amplicon sequencing, we characterised the bacterial gut microbiome of the European lobster using the V4 region of the ribosomal SSU. We compared communities assembled in SBCC with those found LBC and assessed culture and time-dependent determinants of community structure and assembly. Typical of other aquatic invertebrates, the gut of juvenile European lobster mainly harboured Vibrio spp. but became more diverse as the host ages. Assessing phylogenetic structuring of the community, SBCC encouraged more deterministic assembly of the gut microbiome and reduced stochasticity observed in LBC. Furthermore, the gut microbiome of individuals reared in SBCC was significantly more diverse that those reared in LBC. A more diverse gut is thought to be beneficial to host health. In support of this theory, a reduction in bacterial gut diversity was associated with the detection of HgNV in the digestive tract, which was less prevalent in SBCC populations compared to the hatchery. Together, this information suggests that SBCC may support the culture of a healthy population through the assembly of a more beneficial gut community with the potential to provide resistance against infection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial and temporal axes impact ecology of the gut microbiome in juvenile European lobster (Homarus gammarus)</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2019_isme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2019_isme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-van-der-giezen-m-daniels-cl-stentiford-gd-bass-d&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Van der Giezen M, Daniels CL, Stentiford GD, Bass D.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Microbial communities within the gut can markedly impact host health and fitness. To what extent environmental influences affect the differential distribution of these microbial populations may therefore significantly impact the successful farming of the host. Using a sea-based container culture (SBCC) system for the on-growing of European lobster (Homarus gammarus), we tracked the bacterial gut microbiota over a 1-year period. We compared these communities with lobsters of the same cohort, retained in a land-based culture (LBC) system to assess the effects of the culture environment on gut bacterial assemblage and describe the phylogenetic structure of the microbiota to compare deterministic and stochastic assembly across both environments. Bacterial gut communities from SBCCs were generally more phylogenetically clustered, and therefore deterministically assembled, compared to those reared in land-based systems. Lobsters in SBCCs displayed significantly more species-rich and species-diverse gut microbiota compared to those retained in LBC. A reduction in the bacterial diversity of the gut was also associated with higher infection prevalence of the enteric viral pathogen Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). SBCCs may therefore benefit the overall health of the host by promoting the assembly of a more diverse gut bacterial community and reducing the susceptibility to disease.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first clawed lobster virus Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV n. sp.) expands the diversity of the Nudiviridae</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2021_scireports/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-cc-stone-m-bass-d-bateman-ks-van-aerle-r-daniels-cl-van-der-giezen-m-ross-sh-hooper-c-stentiford-gd&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Stone M, Bass D, Bateman KS, van Aerle R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Ross SH, Hooper C, Stentiford GD.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Viral diseases of crustaceans are increasingly recognised as challenges to shellfish farms and fisheries. Here we describe the first naturally-occurring virus reported in any clawed lobster species. Hypertrophied nuclei with emarginated chromatin, characteristic histopathological lesions of DNA virus infection, were observed within the hepatopancreatic epithelial cells of juvenile European lobsters (Homarus gammarus). Transmission electron microscopy revealed infection with a bacilliform virus containing a rod shaped nucleocapsid enveloped in an elliptical membrane. Assembly of PCR-free shotgun metagenomic sequencing produced a circular genome of 107,063 bp containing 97 open reading frames, the majority of which share sequence similarity with a virus infecting the black tiger shrimp: Penaeus monodon nudivirus (PmNV). Multiple phylogenetic analyses confirm the new virus to be a novel member of the Nudiviridae: Homarus gammarus nudivirus (HgNV). Evidence of occlusion body formation, characteristic of PmNV and its closest relatives, was not observed, questioning the horizontal transmission strategy of HgNV outside of the host. We discuss the potential impacts of HgNV on juvenile lobster growth and mortality and present HgNV-specific primers to serve as a diagnostic tool for monitoring the virus in wild and farmed lobster stocks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halioticida noduliformans infection in eggs of lobster (Homarus gammarus) reveals its generalist parasitic strategy in marine invertebrates</title>
      <link>/publications/holt_2018_jip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/holt_2018_jip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;holt-c-foster-r-daniels-cl-van-der-giezen-m-feist-sw-stentiford-gd-bass-d&#34;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Holt C&lt;/u&gt;, Foster R, Daniels CL, van der Giezen M, Feist SW, Stentiford GD, Bass D.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A parasite exhibiting Oomycete-like morphology and pathogenesis was isolated from discoloured eggs of the European lobster (Homarus gammarus) and later found in gill tissues of adults. Group-specific Oomycete primers were designed to amplify the 18S ribosomal small subunit (SSU), which initially identified the organism as the same as the ‘Haliphthoros’ sp. NJM 0034 strain (AB178865.1) previously isolated from abalone (imported from South Australia to Japan). However, in accordance with other published SSU-based phylogenies, the NJM 0034 isolate did not group with other known Haliphthoros species in our Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian phylogenies. Instead, the strain formed an orphan lineage, diverging before the separation of the Saprolegniales and Pythiales. Based upon 28S large subunit (LSU) phylogeny, our own isolate and the previously unidentified 0034 strain are both identical to the abalone pathogen Halioticida noduliformans. The genus shares morphological similarities with Haliphthoros and Halocrusticida and forms a clade with these in LSU phylogenies. Here, we confirm the first recorded occurrence of H. noduliformans in European lobsters and associate its presence with pathology of the egg mass, likely leading to reduced fecundity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
