<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food Security on </title>
    <link>/tags/food-security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Food Security on </description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/food-security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Defining and averting syndemic pathways in aquaculture: a major global food sector</title>
      <link>/publications/stentiford_2023_fronsusfood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/stentiford_2023_fronsusfood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;stentiford-gd-tyler-cr-ellis-rp-bean-tp-mackenzie-s-brugere-c-holt-cc-peeler-ej-christison-kw-rushton-j-bass-d&#34;&gt;Stentiford GD, Tyler CR, Ellis RP, Bean TP, MacKenzie S, Brugere C, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Peeler EJ, Christison KW, Rushton J, Bass D.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Aquaculture now provides half of all aquatic protein consumed globally—with most current and future production occurring in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). Concerns over the availability and application of effective policies to deliver safe and sustainable future supply have the potential to hamper further development of the sector. Creating healthy systems must extend beyond the simple exclusion of disease agents to tackle the host, environmental, and human drivers of poor outcomes and build new policies that incorporate these broader drivers. Syndemic theory provides a potential framework for operationalizing this One Health approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global adoption of aquaculture to supply seafood</title>
      <link>/publications/stentiford_2022_erl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/stentiford_2022_erl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;stentiford-gd-holt-cc&#34;&gt;Stentiford GD, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No abstract! Weird, eh?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;read-the-paper-here&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/ac5c9f/meta&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the paper here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stentiford GD, Holt CC. Global adoption of aquaculture to supply seafood. Environmental Research Letters. 2022 Mar 21;17(4):041003.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A seafood risk tool for assessing and mitigating chemical and pathogen hazards in the aquaculture supply chain</title>
      <link>/publications/stentiford_2022_naturefood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publications/stentiford_2022_naturefood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;stentiford-gd-peeler-ej-tyler-cr-bickley-lk-holt-cc-bass-d-turner-ad-baker-austin-c-ellis-t-lowther-ja-posen-pe-bateman-ks-verner-jeffreys-dw-van-van-aerle-r-stone-dm-paley-r-trent-a-katsiadaki-i-higman-wg-maskrey-bh-devlin-mj-lyons-bp-hartnell-dm-younger-ad-bersuder-p-warford-l-losada-s-clarke-k-hynes-c-dewar-a-greenhill-b-huk-m-franks-j-dal-molin-f-hartnell-re&#34;&gt;Stentiford GD, Peeler EJ, Tyler CR, Bickley LK, &lt;u&gt;Holt CC&lt;/u&gt;, Bass D, Turner AD, Baker-Austin C, Ellis T, Lowther JA, Posen PE, Bateman KS, Verner-Jeffreys DW, van van Aerle R, Stone DM, Paley R, Trent A, Katsiadaki I, Higman WG, Maskrey BH, Devlin MJ, Lyons BP, Hartnell DM, Younger AD, Bersuder P, Warford L, Losada S, Clarke K, Hynes C, Dewar A, Greenhill B, Huk M, Franks J, Dal-Molin F, Hartnell RE.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intricate links between aquatic animals and their environment expose them to chemical and pathogenic hazards, which can disrupt seafood supply. Here we outline a risk schema for assessing potential impacts of chemical and microbial hazards on discrete subsectors of aquaculture—and control measures that may protect supply. As national governments develop strategies to achieve volumetric expansion in seafood production from aquaculture to meet increasing demand, we propose an urgent need for simultaneous focus on controlling those hazards that limit its production, harvesting, processing, trade and safe consumption. Policies aligning national and international water quality control measures for minimizing interaction with, and impact of, hazards on seafood supply will be critical as consumers increasingly rely on the aquaculture sector to supply safe, nutritious and healthy diets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
